A Guide to the Historical Society of Fairfax County, Virginia Records, 1946-2016
Virginia Room, Fairfax County Public Library
The Historical Society of Fairfax County, Virginia Records, 1946-2016
Fairfax County Public Library
MSS 05-01
5.0 linear feet
The Historical Society of Fairfax County, Virginia Records consists of 5.0 linear feet spanning the years 1946-2016. Items include correspondence, meeting minutes, flyers, programs, letterhead, photographs, engraved printing blocks, notes, yearbooks, reports, financial reports, essays, membership lists, membership applications, and floppy disks. Subjects include the creation, events, publications, administrative activities, membership, and finances of the Historical Society of Fairfax County, Virginia.
Historical Society of Fairfax County, Virginia
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
None
Acquisition Information
Records deposited with the Virginia Room over a period of years by the Historical Society of Fairfax County
Historical and Biographical Information
On February 18, 1950, twenty-six Fairfax County citizens met at Woodlawn Plantation at the invitation of Mr. J.W. Rixey-Smith to organize an historical society to preserve historical sites and traditions of Fairfax County. From this meeting began the Historical Society of Fairfax County, which received a charter from the Commonwealth on May 26, 1950. The continued purpose of the organization is to promote and preserve the history of Fairfax County. The historical society continues to do this by locating historical records, hosting annual meetings and lectures, and publishing a biennial yearbook containing historical articles. The original founding members invited 100 people to become charter members prior to opening membership to the general public in 1950. The first annual meeting of the society occurred on June 18th, 1950 at the Jackson House in McLean.
One of the inaugural kick-off events to gain interest in the society was a Heirloom Show and Tour of Historic Houses held at Truro Parish on November 25, 1950. Citizens brought out all sorts of antiques and heirlooms to exhibit. In 1951, the society also undertook a county-wide project of compiling a list of portraits painted before 1850 that were in the possession of local citizens.
In January 1965, the society was instrumental in sponsoring the creation of the Historic Landmarks Preservation Committee, later renamed the Fairfax County History Commission. Beginning in 1975 the society held an annual historical essay contest for students in Fairfax County high schools. Winners received cash prizes and the society published the winning essays in the biennial yearbook. In addition to the yearbook, the society started publishing a newsletter in 1987 but ceased in 2000.
Over the years, the society acquired many historical documents and manuscripts. The society donated most of these documents to the Virginia Room at the City of Fairfax Regional Library and the Fairfax Circuit Court Historic Records Center. The society’s activity has slowed down in recent years and after an eight year lapse, the society will resuming publishing a biennial yearbook in 2017. Membership is open to anyone interested in the historical background of the county. There are typically four meetings a year which includes a lecture on a subject of local history.
Scope and Content
Series 1: Administrative Records, 1950-2016, Boxes 1 and 6
Contains miscellaneous papers relating to the administrative activities of the society. Includes certificates of incorporation, charters, copyright certificates, bylaws, meeting minutes, meeting notices, lists, reports, flyers, newsletters, articles, newspaper clippings, floppy disks, notes, and essays from the society’s annual historical essay contest.
Series 2: Correspondence, 1950-2005, Boxes 1 and 2
Contains correspondence written and received by the historical society. Correspondence written by society members include Henry C. Mackall, Mayo Stuntz, Douglas Mackall, Richard M. Smith, Edith Sprouse, Beth Mitchell, Connie Ring, Richard E. Crouch, Susan G. Leigh and several others. Subjects include membership, meetings, genealogy requests, local history, and society activities. Also included are RSVP cards, letterhead, and envelopes with the society’s logo and address.
Series 3: Membership Records, c. 1950s - 2016, Box 2
Contains membership lists, new member lists, register books, completed membership application forms and cards, and blank membership renewal forms. Lists contain addresses and contact information for members and their dues history. Also included is a roster of members who were interested in saving the Moorefield house (Vienna, Va.) from demolition.
Series 4: Financial Records, 1950-2005, Box 2
Contains expenditures notebook, receipts, account ledger book, and treasurer’s reports. The majority of these documents were maintained by long-time treasurer of the society, Henry C. Mackall. Documents detail the finances and expenditures of the society.
Series 5: Events, 1950-2000, Box 2
Contains flyers, invitations, programs, and notes regarding events the historical society was involved or invited to. Events include the society’s inaugural Heirloom Show and Tour of Historic Houses held in 1951, Fairfax County Heritage Day, Fairfax County’s 240th Anniversary Celebration, Fairfax Heritage Awards, 30th Anniversary of the Fairfax County History Commission, Old Town Hall Centennial, and 200th Birthday of the Fairfax Courthouse.
Series 6: Historical Fairfax County Papers, 1946-1965, Box 2
Over the years, the society acquired many historical documents relating to Fairfax County. Included here are original documents and photocopies of historical documents. Original papers contained are correspondence from the Fauquier County Bar Association and papers from Fairfax attorney and former State-Senator John W. Rust. Photocopies are included of Fairfax County Revolutionary War Surgeon Dr. Benjamin Chapin’s will, Judge James Allen’s papers, an 1873 subscription list of Chantilly Episcopal Church, and meeting minutes of the Fairfax Historical Society.
Series 7: Yearbooks, 1951-2008, Boxes 3, 4 and 6
Contains biennial yearbooks published by the society. Also included are articles, drafts, notes, photographs, order blanks, and engraved printing blocks used in the production of various yearbook issues.
Adjunct Descriptive Data
None
Invoices, copies of checks, and membership applications from 2000-2005 were destroyed.
Index Terms
Historical Society of Fairfax County (Fairfax County, Va.)
Container List
- Series 1: Administrative Records, 1950-2016
  - Certificate of Incorporation, 1950 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Charter of the Historical Society of Fairfax County, 1950-1957 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Copyright Certificate of Registration for Courthouse Logo, 1951 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Bylaws of the Historical Society of Fairfax County, Undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Proposed Bylaws, Undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Meeting Minutes and Notes, 1950-1962 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Meeting Notices, 1981-2016 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - List of Meeting Locations and Dates 1950-1980, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Board of Directors Meeting Agendas, 1976-2004 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Board of Directors Meeting Minutes, 1990-2015 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - List of Officers and Board Members, 1970-2005 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Secretarial Duties, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Commonwealth of Virginia-State Corporation Commission Annual Reports, 1995-1996 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Flyers, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Newspaper Clippings, 1950-1976 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - News Articles, 1992-2002 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Newsletters, 1987-1990 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Newsletters, 1991-2000 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Reports, 1961-1975 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Portrait Information, 1951 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Histories, 1961-1979 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Essay Contest, 1971-1980 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Essay Contest, 1983-1988 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Floppy Disks, 1996-1998 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Website Printouts, 2001-2002 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Minute Book of The Historical Society of Fairfax County, Virginia, Inc., 1950-1994 (Box 6)
- Series 2: Correspondence, 1950-2005
  - American Association of State and Local History Correspondence, 1950 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Lincoln Group of the District of Columbia Correspondence, 1950 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Douglas S. Freeman Correspondence, 1950-1951 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Richard M. Smith Correspondence, 1950-1962 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - General Correspondence, 1950-1969 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Henry C. Mackall Correspondence, 1969-2002 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - General Correspondence, 1971-1972 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - General Correspondence, 1973-1974 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - General Correspondence, 1975-1976 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - General Correspondence, 1977-1980 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Bayard Evans Memorial Fund Correspondence, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - General Correspondence, 1981-1982 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - General Correspondence, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - General Correspondence, 1984-1986 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - General Correspondence, 1987-1988 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - General Correspondence, 1989-1990 (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Richard E. Crouch President's Correspondence, 1990-1993 (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - General Correspondence, 1991-1992 (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - Publications Committee Correspondence, 1991-1992 (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - General Correspondence, 1993-1995 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - General Correspondence, 1996-1997 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - General Correspondence, 1998-1999 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Mosby's Rock Correspondence, 2000-2001 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - General Correspondence, 2000-2002 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - General Correspondence, 2003-2005 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - RSVP Meeting cards, Undated (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Historical Society Courthouse logo, Undated (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Letterhead and Envelopes, Undated (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Series 3: Membership Records, c. 1950s-2016
  - Membership Lists, c. 1950s (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Membership Dues Register Book, 1973-1979 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - New Members Lists, 1978-1994 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Membership Ledger, 1980-1999 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Membership Lists, 1984-1989 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Membership Lists, 1997 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Membership Lists, 1998 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Membership Lists, 1999 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Membership Lists, 2000 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Membership Lists, 2001 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Membership Lists, 2002 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Membership Lists, 2004 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Membership Lists, 2005 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Membership Lists, Undated (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - List of members interested in saving Moorefield, Undated (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - McLean Historical Society Members of Fairfax County Historical Society, 1995-2005 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - New Membership Application Cards (completed), 1984-1988 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Membership Application Forms (completed), 1994-1998 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Membership Renewal Forms (blank), 1998-2016 (Box 2, Folder 28)
- Series 4: Financial Records, 1950-2005
  - Expenditures Notebook, 1950-1952 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Receipts, 1956-1957 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Account Ledger Book, 1983-1984 (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Treasurer's Reports, 1977-1993 (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Treasurer's Reports, 1995-1999 (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Treasurer's Reports, 2000-2001 (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - Treasurer's Reports, 2002-2005 (Box 2, Folder 35)
- Series 5: Events, 1950-2000
  - Heirloom Show and Tour of Historic Houses, Fairfax, Va., 1950 November 25 (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - Fairfax County Heritage Day, 1976 June 6 (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - 240th Anniversary Celebration of Fairfax County, Virginia, 1982 (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - Fairfax Heritage Awards, 1997 (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - Fairfax County History Commission 30th Anniversary, 1998 November 8 (Box 2, Folder 40)
  - Old Town Hall Centennial Celebration, 2000 November 17 (Box 2, Folder 41)
  - 200th Birthday of Fairfax County Courthouse, 2000 (Box 2, Folder 42)
- Series 6: Historical Fairfax County Papers, 1946-1965
  - Fauquier County Bar Association Correspondence, 1946 (Box 2, Folder 43)
  - John W. Rust Papers, 1950-1956 (Box 2, Folder 44)
  - Dr. Benjamin Chapin, Revolutionary War Surgeon, Copy of 1781 Will [photocopy], 1951 February 27 (Box 2, Folder 45)
  - 1873 Subscription List of Christ Church for Chantilly Episcopal Church [photocopy], 1965 January 13 (Box 2, Folder 46)
  - Judge James Allen Papers, 1910-1928 [photocopy], Undated (Box 2, Folder 47)
  - Minutes of Meetings of the Fairfax Historical Society, 1910-1917 [photocopy], Undated (Box 2, Folder 48)
- Series 7: Yearbooks, 1951-2008
  - Yearbook V. 1 - Engraved Printing Block: Fairfax Courthouse, 1951 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Yearbook V. 1 - Engraved Printing Block: Antonia Ford, 1951 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Yearbook V. 1 - Engraved Printing Blocks: Accotink School and J.E.B. Stuart News Article on Mosby's Capture of Gen. Stoughton, 1951 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Yearbook V. 1 - Engraved Printing Blocks: John S. Mosby and Unidentified Building, 1951 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Yearbook V. 1 - Engraved Printing Blocks: Gunnell House and Old Fairfax Elementary School, 1951 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Yearbook V. 1 - Engraved Printing Block: Unidentified Building, 1951 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Yearbook V. 1 - Engraved Printing Block and Cards: Fairfax Courthouse Logo, 1951 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Yearbook V. 1 - Virginia Press Receipt for Engravings Used in Yearbook, 1952 June 18 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Yearbook V. 10 - Introduction, 1969 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Yearbook V. 10 - Mount Vernon’s Architect, 1969 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Yearbook V. 10 - The Gap Line, 1969 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Yearbook V. 10 - Tobacco, Tobacco Hogsheads, and Rolling Roads, 1959 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Yearbook V. 10 - Secessionist Sentiment in Northern Virginia, 1967 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Yearbook V. 10 - James Haley, 1st Va Regt, 1967 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Yearbook V. 10 - Fairfax County Committee of Safety, Undated (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Yearbook V. 10 - Engagement at Blackburn’s Ford, Undated (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Yearbook V. 10 - Fairfax County Portrayed by the Business Directory and Gazetteer, 1906, Undated (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Yearbook V. 10 - Constitution & By-laws Fairfax Medical Society, Undated (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Yearbook V. 10 - Historical Index, Undated (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Yearbook V. 10 - Manuscript Source Records, Undated (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Yearbook V. 11 - Introduction, 1971 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Yearbook V. 11 - George Turberville’s Grant on the Potomac, 1970 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Yearbook V. 11 - Fairfax County Resolutions, Undated (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Yearbook V. 11 - The American Revolution and No. Va, 1971 (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Yearbook V. 11 - Genealogy of the Turberville Family, Undated (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Yearbook V. 11 - Windy Hill Farm, Undated (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Yearbook V. 11 - Official Records of the Colonial Period in Fairfax County, Undated (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - Yearbook V. 11 - Fairfax County in 1887-88, 1962 (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - Yearbook V. 11 - Truro Rectory, 1970 (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - Yearbook V. 11 - Richard Bland Lee of Sully, 1970 (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - Yearbook V. 11 - Yankee Farmers in Northern Virginia, Undated (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - Yearbook V. 13 - Introduction, Etc., 1977 (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - Yearbook V. 14 - Poor Relief in Truro Parish, 1732-1785, Undated (Box 3, Folder 33)
  - Yearbook V. 14 - Development of Postal Service in Fairfax County, 1976-1977 (Box 3, Folder 34)
  - Yearbook V. 15 - Introduction, Etc., 1978-1979 (Box 3, Folder 35)
  - Yearbook V. 15 - Capture and Escape of Capt. J. Owens Berry, Undated (Box 3, Folder 36)
  - Yearbook V. 15 - History of New Alexandria, 1978 (Box 3, Folder 37)
  - Yearbook V. 15 - Address Delivered by Mrs. E.L. Templeman on Lt. William Triplett, 1968 (Box 3, Folder 38)
  - Yearbook V. 15 - Matildaville, Support Town on the Patowmack Canal, 1979 (Box 3, Folder 39)
  - Yearbook V. 15 - Marriage Bonds, 1788, Undated (Box 3, Folder 40)
  - Yearbook V. 15 - St. Timothy’s Chapel, Undated (Box 3, Folder 41)
  - Yearbook V. 15 - John Turley, Tobacco Inspector, Undated (Box 3, Folder 42)
  - Yearbook V. 15 - History of Pleasant Grove and Gunnel’s Chapel Methodist Churches, Undated (Box 3, Folder 43)
  - Yearbook V. 15 - WPA in Fairfax County, Undated (Box 3, Folder 44)
  - Yearbook V. 15 - Poll List for the Election of Burgess, 1741, Undated (Box 3, Folder 45)
  - Yearbook V. 16 - Independent Order of Good Templars, 1980 (Box 3, Folder 46)
  - Yearbook V. 16 - Joseph Leiter, Undated (Box 3, Folder 47)
  - Yearbook V. 16 - Coombe Cottage, Undated (Box 3, Folder 48)
  - Yearbook V. 16 - Fairfax County Marriages Prior to 1853, Undated (Box 3, Folder 49)
  - Yearbook V. 16 - Col. John Colville, 18th Century Gentleman, 1979 (Box 3, Folder 50)
  - Yearbook V. 16 - Capt. Burke Son of Silas, 1980 (Box 3, Folder 51)
  - Yearbook V. 16 - History of Arnon Chapel in Great Falls, Va, 1980 (Box 3, Folder 52)
  - Yearbook V. 16 - Fairfax County Publications, Undated (Box 3, Folder 53)
  - Yearbook V. 19 - Camera Ready Copy, 1983-1985 (Box 6)
  - Yearbook V. 19 - Saga of Shutter's Hill, Appendix A-E, Undated (Box 3, Folder 54)
  - Yearbook V. 19 - Gunnell Family in Fairfax County, Undated (Box 3, Folder 55)
  - Yearbook V. 25 - Photographs, 1994 (Box 3, Folder 56)
  - Yearbook V. 28 - Front and Back Cover, 2001 (Box 3, Folder 57)
  - Yearbook V. 28 - The Bailey Family, Corrections, 2002 (Box 3, Folder 58)
  - Yearbook V. 29 - A Civil War Action at Lewinsville, Virginia, 2003 (Box 3, Folder 59)
  - Yearbook Order Blanks and Inventories, 1978-1999 (Box 3, Folder 60)
  - Historical Society of Fairfax County Yearbook V. 1 [3 copies], 1951 (Box 4)
  - Historical Society of Fairfax County Yearbook V. 2 [6 copies], 1952-1953 (Box 4)
  - Historical Society of Fairfax County Yearbook V. 3 [4 copies], 1954 (Box 4)
  - Historical Society of Fairfax County Yearbook V. 4 [5 copies], 1955 (Box 4)
  - Historical Society of Fairfax County Yearbook V. 5 [7 copies], 1956-1957 (Box 4)
  - Historical Society of Fairfax County Yearbook V. 6 [3 copies], 1958-1959 (Box 4)
  - Historical Society of Fairfax County Yearbook V. 7 [4 copies], 1960-1961 (Box 4)
  - Historical Society of Fairfax County Yearbook V. 8 [5 copies], 1962-1963 (Box 4)
  - Historical Society of Fairfax County Yearbook V. 9 [7 copies], 1964-1965 (Box 4)
  - Historical Society of Fairfax County Yearbook V. 10 [6 copies], 1969 (Box 4)
  - Historical Society of Fairfax County Yearbook V. 11 [6 copies], 1970-1971 (Box 4)
  - Historical Society of Fairfax County Yearbook V. 12 [7 copies], 1971-1973 (Box 4)
  - Historical Society of Fairfax County Yearbook V. 13 [6 copies], 1973-1975 (Box 4)
  - Historical Society of Fairfax County Yearbook V. 14 [5 copies], 1976-1977 (Box 4)
  - Historical Society of Fairfax County Yearbook V. 15 [5 copies], 1978-1979 (Box 4)
  - Historical Society of Fairfax County Yearbook V. 16 [5 copies], 1980 (Box 4)
  - Historical Society of Fairfax County Yearbook V. 17 [7 copies], 1981 (Box 4)
  - Historical Society of Fairfax County Yearbook V. 18 [6 copies], 1982 (Box 4)
  - Historical Society of Fairfax County Yearbook V. 19 [4 copies], 1983 (Box 4)
  - Historical Society of Fairfax County Yearbook V. 20 [6 copies], 1984-1985 (Box 4)
  - Historical Society of Fairfax County Yearbook V. 21 [1 copy], 1986-1988 (Box 5)
  - Historical Society of Fairfax County Yearbook V. 22 [5 copies], 1989-1990 (Box 5)
  - Historical Society of Fairfax County Yearbook V. 23 [2 copies], 1991-1992 (Box 5)
  - Historical Society of Fairfax County Yearbook V. 24 [5 copies], 1993-1994 (Box 5)
  - Historical Society of Fairfax County Yearbook V. 25 [6 copies], 1995-1996 (Box 5)
  - Historical Society of Fairfax County Yearbook V. 26 [3 copies], 1997-1998 (Box 5)
  - Historical Society of Fairfax County Yearbook V. 27 [6 copies], 1999-2000 (Box 5)
  - Historical Society of Fairfax County Yearbook V. 28 [6 copies], 2001-2002 (Box 5)
  - Historical Society of Fairfax County Yearbook V. 29 [6 copies], 2003-2004 (Box 5)
  - Historical Society of Fairfax County Yearbook V. 30 [2 copies], 2005-2006 (Box 5)
  - Historical Society of Fairfax County Yearbook V. 31 [1 copy], 2007-2008 (Box 5)